John F. Bjorklund collection of railroad photographs
Center for Railroad Photography & Art
John F. Bjorklund collection of railroad photographs
1950–2004
1971–2001
Center for Railroad Photography & Art
Bjorklund, John F., 1939-2005
Several color slides were not photographed by John Bjorklund; it is common for photographers to trade photographs from their own personal collections. Additional photographers include: Annett, Ken; Babcock, H.; Black, Tim; Borg, Ken; Chione, Al; Hanifan, Ted; Herbert, L. N.; Kessler, Robert; Koglin, Jim; Lowe, Steve; Rasmussen, Clarence; Schlaepfer, G. L.; Thomas, Jim; Uhelski, John M.
2011.1
17 linear feet 99 metal cartons in 17 archival boxes 55,221 color slides.
Color slides by John F. Bjorklund, from his collection of approximately 55,000 photographs. The collection focuses on American and Canadian railroads from the late 1960s through the early 2000s, spanning much of North America.
Selected Search Terms
Countries
Canada; United States
States/Provinces
Alberta; Arizona; Arkansas; British Columbia; California; Colorado; Idaho; Illinois; Indiana; Iowa; Kansas; Kentucky; Louisiana; Manitoba; Michigan; Minnesota; Missouri; Montana; Nebraska; Nevada; New Brunswick; New Hampshire; New Jersey; New Mexico; New York; North Carolina; North Dakota; Nova Scotia; Ohio; Oklahoma; Ontario; Oregon; Pennsylvania; Prince Edward Island; Quebec; Saskatchewan; South Dakota; Tennessee; Texas; Utah; Vermont; Virginia; Washington; Washington, D.C.; West Virginia; Wisconsin; Wyoming
Railroads
Algoma Central Railway; Ann Arbor Railroad; Atchison, Topeka, & Santa Fe Railway; Arcade & Attica Railroad; Arkansas & Missouri Railroad; Baltimore & Ohio Railroad; Bath & Hammondsport Railroad; Bessemer & Lake Erie Railroad; Burlington Northern Railroad; Butte, Anaconda & Pacific Railway; California Western Railroad; California Zephyr; Canadian National Railway; Chicago, Burlington & Quincy Railroad; Chicago & Illinois Midland Railway; Chicago, Madison & Northern Railway; Chicago & North Western Railway; Chicago, Milwaukee, St. Paul & Pacific Railroad; Chicago, Rock Island & Pacific Railroad; Chicago South Shore & South Bend Railroad; Columbia & Cowlitz Railway; Concord & Claremont Railroad; Conrail; Chesapeake & Ohio Railway; Clinchfield Railroad; CSX Transportation; Delaware & Hudson Railway; Denver & Rio Grande Western Railroad; Detroit & Mackinac Railway; Detroit, Toledo & Ironton Railroad; East Broad Top Railroad; Elgin, Joliet & Eastern Railway; Erie Railroad; Erie Lackawanna Railway; Escanaba & Lake Superior Railroad; Essex Terminal Railway; Grand Trunk Western Railroad; Greater Cleveland Regional Transit Authority; Great Northern Railway; Green Bay & Western Railroad; Green Mountain Railroad; Gulf, Mobile & Ohio Railroad; Hillsdale County Railway Company; Illinois Central Gulf Railroad; Illinois Central Railroad; Illinois Terminal Railroad; Indiana & Ohio Railway; Indiana Railroad Company; Kansas City Southern Railway; Keweenaw Central Railroad; Kyle Railroad; Lake Superior & Ishpeming Railroad; Lehigh Valley Railroad; Long Island Rail Road; Louisiana & North West Railroad; Louisville & Nashville Railroad; McCloud River Railroad; Metra; Michigan Northern Railway; The Milwaukee Electric Railway & Light Company; Milwaukee Road; Minneapolis, Northfield & Southern; Missouri-Kansas-Texas Railroad; Missouri Pacific Railroad; Monon Railroad; New York Central Railroad; Norfolk & Western Railway; Northern Pacific Railway; Ontario Northland Railway; Oregon, California & Eastern Railroad; Pacific Great Eastern Railway; Penn Central Railroad; Pennsylvania Railroad; Pittsburg & Shawmut Railroad; Port Huron & Detroit Railroad; Prescott & Northwestern Railroad; Reading Company; Richmond, Fredericksburg & Potomac Railroad; Riverside & Great Northern Railway; Roaring Camp & Big Trees Railroad; Soo Line Railroad; South Simcoe Railway; Southern Railway; Southern Pacific Railroad; St. Louis-San Francisco Railway; Union Pacific Railroad; Temiskaming & Northern Ontario Railway; Toledo, Lake Erie & Western Railway; Toledo, Peoria & Western Railway; Toronto Transit Commission; Tuscola & Saginaw Bay Railroad; Twin City Rapid Transit Company; Western Maryland Railway; Western Pacific Railroad; Weyerhaeuser Woods Railroad; Wisconsin Central Railway; Wisconsin Central Transportation
Subjects
Photography of railroads; Railroads--Pictorial works
Biographical Note
John was born in Tacoma, Washington, to Walter and Barbara Bjorklund. Walter was a Northern Pacific Division Engineer whose frequent division shifts on the railroad and engineering assignments allowed John to grow up and absorb, learn, and enjoy most all of the Northern Pacific in the west. The family lived in Billings, Montana, during John's elementary school years, and later in St. Paul, Minnesota. This exposure led to John's love of the Northern Pacific, which carried on into the Burlington Northern, but John also had huge soft spots for the Milwaukee Road, Erie Lackawanna and nice big passengers trains, like the NP's flagship North Coast Limited.
Following college at the University of Minnesota in St. Paul (the real U. of M., as he would say), John served two years in the Army. He was stationed at Fort Knnox and engaged in psychological testing. Following his discharge in 1965, he returned to St. Paul and found employment at the Ford Motor Company. Ford soon transferred him to Detroit, where he would remain for the rest of his life. He retired in 1999, having ascended the corporate level as a traffic analyst. His work involved coordinating the transportation of auto body parts and finished automobiles by rail and truck. Through professional contacts, he gained many great friends on the railroads.
Besides railroad photography, John had a great love for the opera and classical music. He put together several dissolve slide shows of railroad photographs set to classical music, finding just the right ballad or instrumental for each photo sequence. More importantly, John possessed a keen memory. Friends called him a "walking hard drive" for his uncanny ability to recall details, dates, and locations.
When he started photography in the late '60s, there were numerous signal towers and stations still in use, which John often incorporated in his photos. He loved signals above all, and various types appeared frequently in his photos as both subjects and compositional elements. His favorites by far were semaphores, or "blades" as he called them. John made it a point to cover as much as he could of disappearing aspects of railroading before they disappeared.
This interest and drive allowed John to cover a great deal of the U.S. and a good portion of Canada during his photography career. Besides traveling with most of the Detroit Tuesday Night Live group (a group of Detroit-area railroad photographers who meet on Tuesday nights to share photos), John was also a frequent photography partner with Jim Thomas, Mike Schafer, Doug Harrop, Emery Gulash, Jeff Mast, Bob Kessler, and Jim Koglin. Kessler, Koglin, and Bjorklund traveled together so frequently during the last 10 years of John's life that friends dubbed them the infamous "Group of Three."
In the early 1980s, John commissioned a painting by noted railroad artist Larry Fisher. Based on one of John's photos, it shows one of his favorite locations that contained two of his favorite railroads: the Northern Pacific and the Milwaukee Road near Iris, Montana. The painting features the Milaukee Road's Olympian Hiawatha with electric "boxcab" no. E14 overtaking a westbound NP freight headed by Z6 "Challenger" steam locomotive no. 5117.
John is survived by his wife, Rose, whom he married late in life in 1990, and brothers Drew of Minneapolis and Charles of New York. He is fondly remembered by many great friends in the Detroit area, and around the U.S. and Canada.
Scope and Content Note
The John Bjorklund collection includes approximately 55,000 35mm Kodak color slides. The photographs range from 1950-2004, covering American and Canadian railroads, spanning much of North America.
The collection has a strong focus on the American and Canadian railroads including an emphasis on the Midwest and Pacific Northwest with Ann Arbor Railroad, Burlington Northern Railroad, Chicago and North Western Railway, Milwaukee Road, Norfolk and Western Railway, Southern Pacific Railroad, and Union Pacific Railroad. There is also a strong emphasis on Canadian railroads with Canadian National Railway and Canadian Pacific Railway.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged by the original order of John Bjorklund, which consists of 99 metal cartons categorized alphabetically by railroad company.
Administrative Information
Provenance
John Bjorklund's widow, Mrs. Rose Bjorklund, donated his photograph collection to the Center in 2011. Center members Michael R. Valentine and Jeff Mast helped immensely with the acquisition.
© 2016, Center for Railroad Photograph & Art
Digitized Versions Available
Images from this collection have been digitized and are available through CRP&A's online collection portal.
Related CRP&A Publications
Lothes, Scott, ed. Significant Images of Railroading. Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2016.
- 1967–1980, Ann Arbor 1; 535 color slides (Box Box 01, Carton Carton 01)
  States/Provinces
  Michigan; Ohio; Wisconsin
  Railroads
  Ann Arbor Railroad
- 1980–1982, Ann Arbor 2; 571 color slides (Box Box 01, Carton Carton 02)
- 1972–1985, Ann Arbor 3; 425 color slides (Box Box 01, Carton Carton 03)
  Michigan; Ohio
- 1967–1985, ATSF 1; 661 color slides (Box Box 01, Carton Carton 04)
  Arizona; California; Colorado; Illinois; Kansas; Michigan; Missouri; New Mexico; Oklahoma; Texas
  Atchison, Topeka, & Santa Fe Railway
- 1985–1990, ATSF 2; 677 color slides (Box Box 01, Carton Carton 05)
  Arizona; California; Colorado; Illinois; Iowa; Kansas; New Mexico
- 1978–1995, ATSF 3; 335 color slides (Box Box 01, Carton Carton 06)
  Arizona; Idaho; Illinois; Iowa; Kansas; Missouri; Montana; North Dakota; Oregon; South Dakota; Washington; Wyoming
- 1985–1990, ATSF 2; 677 color slides (Box Box 01, Carton Carton 05)
- 1978–1995, ATSF 3; 335 color slides (Box Box 01, Carton Carton 06)
- 1970–1973, BN 1; 644 color slides (Box Box 02, Carton Carton 07)
  Illinois; Minnesota; Montana; North Dakota; Texas; Washington
  Burlington Northern Railroad
- 1973–1975, BN 2; 617 color slides (Box Box 02, Carton Carton 08)
  Idaho; Illinois; Minnesota; Montana; Oregon; Washington
- 1975–1978, BN 3; 578 color slides (Box Box 02, Carton Carton 09)
  California; Colorado; Idaho; Illinois; Montana; North Dakota; Oregon; Washington; Wisconsin; Wyoming
- 1978–1980, BN 4; 615 color slides (Box Box 02, Carton Carton 10)
  Colorado; Illinois; Missouri; Montana; Nebraska; North Dakota; Oregon; South Dakota; Washington; Wisconsin
- 1980, BN 5; 631 color slides (Box Box 02, Carton Carton Carton 11)
  Montana; North Dakota; South Dakota; Wyoming
- 1980–1984, BN 6; 661 color slides (Box Box 02, Carton Carton 12)
  Colorado; Florida; Idaho; Illinois; Iowa; Kansas; Minnesota; Missouri; Montana; Nebraska; Oregon; South Dakota; Texas; Washington; Wyoming
- 1984–1988, BN 7; 673 color slides (Box Box 03, Carton Carton 13)
  Colorado; Illinois; Iowa; Kansas; Michigan; Minnesota; Missouri; Montana; New Mexico; Oregon; Texas; Washington; Wyoming
- 1952–1996, BN 8; 597 color slides (Box Box 03, Carton Carton 14)
  Illinois; Iowa; Kansas; Minnesota; Montana; Nebraska; North Dakota; Oklahoma; Oregon; Texas; Washington; Wisconsin; Wyoming
- 1997–2004, BN 9; 568 color slides (Box Box 03, Carton Carton 15)
  Colorado; Idaho; Illinois; Minnesota; Missouri; New Mexico; Oklahoma; Washington; Wisconsin
- 1977–1984, B&O 2; 612 color slides (Box Box 03, Carton Carton 16)
  Illinois; Indiana; New York; Ohio; Pennsylvania; West Virginia
  Baltimore & Ohio Railroad
- 1979–1987, B&O 3; 573 color slides (Box Box 03, Carton Carton 17)
  Indiana; Maryland; Ohio; Pennsylvania; West Virginia
- 1967–1985, Cal Zephyr/PGE; 668 color slides (Box Box 03, Carton Carton 18)
  British Columbia; California; Colorado; Illinois; Nebraska; New York; Pennsylvania; Utah
  California Zephyr; Delaware & Hudson Railway; Pacific Great Eastern Railway
- 1967–1982, CNR 1; 725 color slides (Box Box 04, Carton Carton 19)
  British Columbia; Manitoba; Nova Scotia; Ontario; Quebec; Saskatchewan
  Canadian National Railway
- 1974–1980, CNR 2; 586 color slides (Box Box 04, Carton Carton 20)
  Manitoba; Ontario; Quebec
- 1980–1986, CNR 3; 767 color slides (Box Box 04, Carton Carton 21)
  British Columbia; Ontario; Quebec
- 1986–1989, CNR 4; 638 color slides (Box Box 04, Carton Carton 22)
  Ontario; Quebec
- 1973–2004, CNR 5; 630 color slides (Box Box 04, Carton Carton 23)
  Illinois; Indiana; Michigan; Minnesota; Ohio; Ontario; Quebec; Wisconsin
- 1966–1976, CNW 1; 602 color slides (Box Box 04, Carton Carton 24)
  Illinois; Kansas; Michigan; Minnesota; Missouri; Wisconsin
  Chicago & North Western Railway
- 1976–1977, CNW 2; 602 color slides (Box Box 05, Carton Carton 25)
  Iowa; Illinois; Minnesota; South Dakota
- 1977–1980, CNW 3; 599 color slides (Box Box 05, Carton Carton 26)
  Iowa; Illinois; Minnesota; North Dakota; South Dakota; Wisconsin; Wyoming
- 1973–1987, CNW 4; 630 color slides (Box Box 05, Carton Carton 27)
  Iowa; Illinois; Kansas; Michigan; Minnesota; Missouri; Nebraska; South Dakota; Wisconsin
- 1971–2004, CNW 5; 538 color slides (Box Box 05, Carton Carton 28)
  Iowa; Illinois; Kansas; Kentucky; Maine; Massachusetts; Michgian; Minnesota; Missouri; Nebraska; Nova Scotia; Prince Edward Island; Quebec; South Dakota
- 1981–1986, Conrail 4; 636 color slides (Box Box 05, Carton Carton 29)
  Illinois; Indiana; Michigan; Missouri; New Jersey; New York; Ohio; Ontario; Pennsylvania
  Conrail
- 1986–1989, Conrail 5; 638 color slides (Box Box 05, Carton Carton 30)
  Illinois; Indiana; Michigan; New Jersey; Ohio; Ontario; Pennsylvania
- 1989–1999, Conrail 6; 627 color slides (Box Box 06, Carton Carton 31)
  Illinois; Indiana; Maryland; Michigan; New Hampshire; New York; Ohio; Pennsylvania; Washington, D.C.
- 1979–1999, Conrail 7; 230 color slides (Box Box 06, Carton Carton 32)
  Massachusetts; New Hampshire; New York; Ohio; Vermont
- 1966–1977, C&O 1; 598 color slides (Box Box 06, Carton Carton 33)
  Illinois; Indiana; Michigan; Ohio; Ontario
  Chesapeake & Ohio Railway
- 1973–1981, C&O 2; 625 color slides (Box Box 6, Carton Carton 34)
  Kentucky; Michigan; Ohio; Virginia; West Virginia
- 1981–1988, C&O 3 to CSXT; 628 color slides (Box Box 6, Carton Carton 35)
  Illinois; Indiana; Kentucky; Michigan; Ohio; Ontario; Pennsylvania; West Virginia; Wisconsin
  Chesapeake & Ohio Railway; CSX Transportation
- 1967–1984, CPR 1; 684 color slides (Box Box 6, Carton Carton 36)
  Alberta; British Columbia; New Brunswick; Nova Scotia; Ontario; Quebec; Saskatchewan
  Canadian Pacific Railway
- 1971–1984, CPR 2; 527 color slides (Box Box 7, Carton Carton 37)
  Alberta; British Columbia; Michigan; Ontario; Quebec
- 1983–1987, CPR 3; 646 color slides (Box Box 7, Carton Carton 38)
- 1987–2000, CPR 4/SSR; 634 color slides (Box Box 7, Carton Carton 39)
  British Columbia; Illinois; Michigan; New York; Ontario; Pennsylvania; Quebec; Wisconsin
  Canadian Pacific Railway; South Simcoe Railway
- 2000–2003, CPR 5; 201 color slides (Box Box 7, Carton Carton 40)
  Indiana; Minnesota; Ontario; Wisconsin
- 1972–2004, CPR/N&W 7; 596 color slides (Box Box 7, Carton Carton 41)
  Illinois; Indiana; North Carolina; Ohio; Ontario; South Carolina; Tennessee; Virginia; West Virginia
  Clinchfield Railroad; Norfolk and Western Railway
- 1971–2001, CSS&SB 1; 627 color slides (Box Box 7, Carton Carton 42)
  Illinois; Indiana
  Chicago South Shore & South Bend Railroad
- 1970–2001, CSS&SB 2/GBW; 331 color slides (Box Box 8, Carton Carton 43)
  Indiana; Minnesota; Wisconsin
  Chicago South Shore & South Bend Railroad; Green Bay & Western Railroad
- 1988–1992, CSXT 4; 630 color slides (Box Box 8, Carton Carton 44)
  Illinois; Indiana; Kentucky; Maryland; Michigan; Ohio; Ontario; Pennsylvania; Tennessee; Virginia; Washington, D.C.; West Virginia
  CSX Transportation; Richmond, Fredericksburg & Potomac Railroad
- 1993–1999, CSXT 5; 635 color slides (Box Box 8, Carton Carton 45)
  Illinois; Indiana; Kentucky; Maryland; Michigan; Ohio; Pennsylvania; Virginia; West Virginia
  CSX Transportation